<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise concerning schism and schismaticks wherein the chief grounds &amp; principles of a late separation from the Church of England, are considered and answered / by Henry Hellier ...</title>
            <author>Hellier, Henry, 1662?-1697.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1697</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1381</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20518</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12175892</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12175892</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 601:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise concerning schism and schismaticks wherein the chief grounds &amp; principles of a late separation from the Church of England, are considered and answered / by Henry Hellier ...</title>
                  <author>Hellier, Henry, 1662?-1697.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Smith for Jo. Crosley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Schism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55533:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE CONCERNING <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks;</hi> Wherein the Chief <hi>Grounds &amp; Principles</hi> Of a Late SEPARATION FROM THE <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH of ENGLAND,</hi> ARE Conſidered and Anſwered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Hellier,</hi> D.D. Fellow of <hi>C.C.C. Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Richard Smith</hi> for <hi>Jo. Croſley</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Oxford,</hi> MDCXCVII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:55533:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55533:2"/>
            <head>A TREATISE CONCERNING Schiſm, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THERE have been many Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes publiſhed about <hi>Schiſm</hi> ſince the late Revolution, and moſt of them by Men averſe to the preſent Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; who have quoted divers Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences out of the ancient Fathers, which they ſay, make againſt us; although they will ſerve, according as the caſe is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſtated, either of one ſide or the other. They call us who do approve of the preſent Government, Schiſmaticks;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55533:3"/>and themſelves the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who have ſeparated themſelves from it; accuſing us of Immoralities in our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; of all the miſchiefs that are done in the Wars; of ſetting up Anti-Biſhops; concluding that we are without the Church, and that there is no Salvation to be had among us in the ordinary way. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it can be no unſeaſonable work to enquire into the nature of Schiſm impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, and into the ways whereby Men may become Schiſmaticks, in order to the clearing ſuch as are innocent from this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and to the charging it in the right place, and on the Perſons that are truly guilty of it. And ſeeing our Adverſaries have taken ſo much liberty of Speech againſt us, as after they have called us Schiſmaticks, and ſaid we are in a ſtate of Damnation, to boaſt of and print Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues of their Books unanſwered; It is but reaſonable that any Man on our part ſhould be heard alſo, that hath a mind to ſpeak, without being blamed only for writing againſt them, much leſs for indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent ſtating of the caſe; for they have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55533:3"/>given ſufficient cauſe for both: But this latter is the thing which I principally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to do; namely, to give a ſtate of the Caſe, or to conſider the rational part of the Subject; which ſeems hitherto to have been moſt neglected, although it is of the greateſt uſe. For if the nature of Schiſm in general, and the ways whereby Men do become Schiſmaticks, are once well underſtood, it will be eaſie to explain the Sentences commonly quoted out of the Fathers, and to make uſe of them if we pleaſe, againſt our Adverſaries; or it will be lawful to reject them, although there will be no need of that; for there are none of them that I know of, which, after a Man hath duly conſidered of the Subject, will ſeem to favour them. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make a general Diſcourſe on this Subject, and alſo to include particular matters within as ſhort a compaſs as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniently may be, I ſhall endeavour to ſhew.
<list>
                  <item>1. What Schiſm is, and how the Members of the Church may become guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it.</item>
                  <item>2. I ſhall ſpeak ſomething alſo of the ſinfulneſs and inconvenience of it,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55533:4"/>to the intent that we may avoid it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us conſider what Schiſm is, and how the Members of the Church may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty of it.</p>
            <p>As for the word <hi>Schiſm,</hi> it ſignifies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the cutting or cleaving of a ſolid Body, from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; hence it is tranſlated to denote diverſity of Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Profeſſions, in thoſe that once appeared at leaſt to be agreed in them; for they that never were united, cannot be ſaid to be cut aſunder. And according to this metaphorical Acceptation, Schiſm is a breach of Unity in any Society what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever: But common uſe and cuſtom hath applied it only to that which divideth the Unity of the Church.</p>
            <p>Yet not the bare Separation, but giving the cauſe of Separation, makes the Schiſm. Whereſoever a Schiſm is, each Party is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided or ſeparated from the other, but each Party is not in a ſtate of Schiſm; that is, doth not give the cauſe of Separation, unleſs it ſo falls out, as it ſometimes may, that both of them are in fault, neither doing its part towards the maintaining of Agreement,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55533:4"/>ſo far as is neceſſary to be preſervation of Unity, in order to one common end.</p>
            <p>Now, as many ways as there are, for the Members of the Church to profeſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves united one with another, with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to matters concerning them, as they are the Church and Congregation of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian People: So many there are alſo for one or more Members to become Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matical, by breaking off that Union in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, which is a Duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent on them,</p>
            <p>I ſpeak of Union which relates to Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters concerning them, as they are Members of the Church: Whence, not every paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Heat, not every Quarrel, not every Suit of Law, not every War, not every Faction or Sedition among the People doth make a Schiſm.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak alſo of Union in outward Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For, tho' there is an internal Union and Communion of all God's faithful Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in regard they have the ſame Faith, and the ſame Hope, and do practice the ſame Chriſtian Virtues; and in default of theſe, or any one of theſe, a Man in ſome
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55533:5"/>ſort cuts himſelf off from thoſe faithful People, and from the Portion which doth belong to them, and ſo the ſecret Infidel, and the ſecret Sinner, may be ſaid to be ſeparated now; for they are none of Chriſt's, and ſhall hear that Sentence in the ſeparation of good and bad Men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, <hi>Depart from me, for I know you not:</hi> Yet this is a matter not peculiarly belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Schiſm, but common to it with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry other Sin, and therefore, in that Senſe I ſhall not now conſider it, but only as it is a Breach of external Communion, and Separation as to outward Profeſſion; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this may be committed as well as any other Sin in the Mind alſo, by a Man's intending or purpoſing to leave the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Communion of the Church, when perhaps he hath not as yet actually done it.</p>
            <p>Now, as the outward Unity or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of every Society appears in the apt Order of the Members one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and Demeanour one towards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, according to their reſpective States and Conditions, as in one Houſe, one Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55533:5"/>one Kingdom: So does the Unity of the Church conſiſt in Mens acting accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their juſt Relations, as Members of the Church, in keeping fair Correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and retaining a due Agreement in Doctrine of Faith and Morals, and in Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline; that is to ſay, Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the things that belong to it, as being requiſit to the due Adminiſtration and right Management of it.</p>
            <p>And this Unity is conſiſtent with ſeveral things, ſeemingly dividing Perſons as Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church, and that partly even in the aforeſaid reſpects; with diverſity of Spiritual Gifts and Functions; with diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Opinions, as to Matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; with Eccleſiaſtical Diſputes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions; with various Judgments and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions, as to particular Circumſtances and Caſes relating to Moral Actions; with Canons and Conſtitutions of divers kinds; with difference in Ceremonies, or other parts of Diſcipline in divers Countries, or divers Parts of the ſame Country, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſeveral Exigencies of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and according to the Diſcretion or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:55533:6"/>Approbation of the Governors Civil or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, as it doth concern them. All theſe things may be, and yet the Church continue ſtill the ſame, as <hi>the Queen in a Veſture of Gold-wrought about with divers Colours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, Church-Cenſures may go on, and Perſons be Excommunicated; and yet, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they wilfully continue under Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, no Schiſm be made; becauſe they do not cut themſelves off from the Church, but are cut off by others; and therefore are not as Schiſmaticks, A <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.11</note> 
               <hi>Condemned of themſelves,</hi> as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Schiſm therefore is a wilfull breaking off of that outward Unity, which one or more Members ought to maintain with the reſt. A Schiſmatick or Schiſmaticks are, that one, or thoſe many Perſons, who do publickly refuſe to act according to his or their juſt Relations, as Members of the Church, in the ſtation wherein they are placed. Or, to ſpeak more briefly, a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick is that Member of the Church, which diſowns and cuts it ſelf off from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55533:6"/>the reſt; either contemning and rejecting the other Members,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.21.</note> as <hi>if the Eye ſhall ſay to the Hand, I have no need of thee;</hi> or again, <hi>The Head to the Feet, I have no need of you:</hi> Or elſe encroaching and breaking in upon the Rights of other Members, as if the <hi>Foot ſhall ſay,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> 15.16.</note> becauſe I am not the Hand,</hi> or <hi>not the Head, I am not of the Body,</hi> and will not be of the Body: Or Laſtly, refuſing to communicate its Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the reſt, not <hi>diſtributing to the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities of the Saints,</hi> not ſuffering and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing with the other Members, the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers not <hi>having the ſame Care</hi> according to their different places and capacities <hi>one for another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.25.</note> according to the Expreſſion of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>To know therefore who is a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and who not, it will be neceſſary to conſider, in ſome general Terms at leaſt, the Relations wherein Men may be, and the ſeveral Cauſes or Pretences of ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, with regard to ſuch Relations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring withal, ſo far as in a ſhort Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of this Nature conveniently may be, which are unlawful, and which are good and ſufficient.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:55533:7"/>
            <p>And Firſt, As there is an Unity in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, which ought to be maintained by all Chriſtian Churches throughout the World, they being all reconciled to God in <hi>One Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2.16. 1 Cor, 12.13.</note> and <hi>Baptized into One Body,</hi> and <hi>made to drink into One Spirit,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called <hi>One Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17. 1 Cor. 12.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> whereof our Lord is the <hi>Head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.15, 16.</note> 
               <hi>from whom the whole Body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every Joynt ſupplyeth, according to the effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual working in the meaſure of every part, maketh encreaſe of the Body, unto the edify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſelf in love.</hi> So there may be a Breach made of this Unity by any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, and thereby whole Churches may become Schiſmatical. Whole Churches in reſpect of the whole Body of Chriſtians, have ſuch Relation, as ſingle Members have, with Regard to any particular Church: They therefore, as well as ſingle Members of particular Churches, may fall into Schiſm, when either in expreſs Terms, or by neceſſary conſequence, they break off their Communion and Friendly Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with the reſt; which may be done ſeveral ways, 1. By profeſſing a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55533:7"/>Faith: Or, 2. Different <hi>Agenda</hi> or Morals. 3. By different Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; either as to the <hi>Species</hi> or kind of Government, or as to the manner of exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſing of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They may become guilty of Schiſm, by profeſſing a different Faith, or appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting different Creeds in any Material Point from other Churches: For Chriſtian Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion doth not require, but forbid us to have Fellowſhip with thoſe who do not hold the Truth, as to the Subſtantials of Chriſtian Religion. The Body of Chriſt hath but <hi>One Faith;</hi> and conſidering that the main Points of Faith have ſuch Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon our Lives and Actions, and are of ſo high importance to every one of us, we ought to <hi>Contend earneſtly for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 3.</note> and to <hi>withdraw</hi> our <hi>ſelves</hi> from thoſe who <hi>teach otherwiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5.</note> 
               <hi>and conſent not to whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, even the words of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3.</note> 
               <hi>and to the Doctrine which is accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Godlineſs.</hi> Not but that Chriſtians may differ, and diſpute, and err about Matters of leſs Moment, or ways of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55533:8"/>the True Faith not ſo clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, without either actually ſeparating themſelves from the Church, or deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be cut off from it, except they do oblige Men to concur with them, and to profeſs a Belief of their Errors: For then we may, and ought to depart from them; it being not lawful for any one, to profeſs he believes that to be true, which at the ſame time he takes to be an Error, even in a matter of the ſmalleſt moment.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They may become guilty of Schiſm, by making wrong Profeſſions <hi>de Agendis,</hi> or concerning Morals: For none ought to concur with any Man, or any number of Men, in that which is immoral. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord is only commendable in that which is good, not in that which is evil. To profeſs an Immorality, is not only to do an immoral thing, (the profeſſion of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſinful Act) but it is worſe than do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame immoral thing that is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to ſuch Profeſſion: It is a ſin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted with deliberation, greater than commonly precedes the Act of Sin; it makes us perſevere and continue in ſin;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:55533:8"/>it tends to the ſeducing and deſtroying others in a more eminent degree than the Act. If any Man therefore ſhall teach Doctrines manifeſtly contradictory to any part of the Moral Law; if a Man ſays, inſtead of, <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother, Thou ſhalt not honour thy Father or thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> Inſtead of, <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers; Let ſome men not be ſubject to the Higher Powers,</hi> and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains this Doctrine in Oppoſition to the Members of his own or other Churches, he is a Schiſmatick. But he that allows of thoſe Precepts, and knows not who is his King, or who is his Father, is miſtaken in the Perſon, not in the Commandment; or at moſt, he is only miſtaken about the Laws of the Land, which (tho' they do oblige in Conſcience when known, yet) it is not every Man's buſineſs, nor doth lye in every Man's power perfectly to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand: And an Error in theſe, does not always imply a miſunderſtanding the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God. He that errs in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of ſome Moral Points; as, in ſhewing, How a Man muſt honour his
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55533:9"/>King or his Father, or in ſetting the Bounds and Meaſures of Obedience to them; or in ſuch a matter as I am now about, in ſtating the Caſe of Schiſm, is not preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be eſteemed guilty of Schiſm: For a Miſtake, though profeſſed in Matters leſs principal, either of Faith or Morals, unleſs it makes void the general Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſome plain Article of Faith, will not make a Man a Schiſmatick. If it did, conſidering how little ſome do underſtand how to explain the Articles of their Faith, how apt thoſe that have a competent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them; are to differ in their manner of explaining them, how various Mens Notions are about ſeveral Points of Caſuiſtical Divinity, and Commentaries on Morals contained in the Commandments; and how difficult it is to ſuppoſe, that Men will be agreed in every Circumſtance of them, the Church would always abound with Schiſmaticks, and there would be no remedy for it: Such things therefore are to be born with in all Communions, as being unavoidable in this Life, where we are ſubject to Errors, and our Knowledge
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55533:9"/>is only <hi>in part;</hi> unleſs the Doctrines be of very ill and dangerous conſequence, obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately taught, and earneſtly preſs'd upon us, and our Concurrence required in them, as a Condition of Communion.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall be interpreted Concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence? He that hears a Man preach falſe Doctrine in the Church, or read an Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wherein ſomething is ſaid againſt his Opinion; or he that hears ſomething in the Common-Prayers, or in the Pulpit-prayer before Sermon, which by reaſon of ſome Circumſtances he does diſlike, cannot be ſaid to concur in all Doctrines ſo taught, or in all Prayers ſo put up: And therefore, it is not a ſufficient Cauſe to make a ſeparate Congregation, that we diſlike the Title given to the King, or any other Perſon there mentioned; nor are theſe immoral things in their own nature, but on the account of Circumſtances of Mens doing them againſt their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And indeed, I do thus far agree with our new Separatiſts, That whoſoever thinks the King to be an Unjuſt Poſſeſſor, and to keep the Rightful One out of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55533:10"/>Throne, ought not to be ſo much as preſent at our Publick Faſts, Thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whilſt he continues under that Error, becauſe no Man ought to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Conſcience: But even ſuch an one hath not ſufficient reaſon to forſake our Communion altogether, unleſs he be forced to give conſent to ſomething that he thinks unlawful, offered up in the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Prayers, which a Man's bare preſence doth not always imply: For then almoſt all thoſe things that I excluded in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this Diſcourſe, would produce a Schiſm. We ſhall not have a Diſpute about a Prince's Title, a Civil War, or War with a Foreign Nation, or ſo much as a Suit of Law, or Quarrel with our Neighbour, or a Deſign thwarting his in the common Tranſactions of Human Life; but there will follow alſo among us different Apprehenſions and Opinions concerning the juſtice or injuſtice of them; and conſequently, concerning certain paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in our Publick Prayers which relate to them; and thereupon we may think it unlawful to ſay ſome words, or at leaſt to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:55533:10"/>take them in the ſame ſenſe that others commonly do, and ſo make a Schiſm: And when there is a Diviſion of the Church, whereby New Paſtors and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors are introduced, and lay claim to the ſame Dioceſes or Pariſhes, how ſhall it be reconciled, although the Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that occaſioned it ſhould be brought to an end? How many would our Diviſions be, if all the Factions that ever were in the State, ſhould have made a Schiſm in the Church alſo? But theſe indeed are Matters which are not ſimply immoral in their own nature, but only by reaſon of Circumſtances relating to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons; neither do they tend to the Overthrow of the Churches Faith or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals; nor are they of long continuance; but as particular Perſons or their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances alter, ceaſe of themſelves. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch Prayers, if not very many and frequent, ought to be tolerated, even by thoſe by whom they may not be ſaid, to avoid a greater Evil, <hi>viz.</hi> The Deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Church, and laſting Depravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Piety and good Morals, the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55533:11"/>conſequences of Separations made from the Church upon the account of them.</p>
            <p>Much leſs may we ſeparate our ſelves from all thoſe who are any way guilty of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moral Actions, as ſome <note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatians, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Schiſmaticks pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to do of old: But I think we have had none ſuch among us of late, unleſs they may be eſteemed of this Number, who hold themſelves obliged to ſeparate from us, only<note n="†" place="margin">See the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of the new Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, p. 1.</note> becauſe we have taken Oaths which they account unlawful. A Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from all bad Men, is not only unreaſonable, but in this Life, impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Hence the Church of Chriſt is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in H. Scripture to a <hi>Floor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3.12.</note> on which is <hi>Wheat</hi> and <hi>Chaff;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luc. 3.17.</note> to a <hi>Net,</hi> which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives <hi>Fiſhes good</hi> and <hi>bad;</hi> to a <hi>Marriage Feaſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.47, 48</note> to which <hi>many are called,</hi> but <hi>few</hi> of them <hi>are choſen;</hi> to a <hi>Fold,</hi> having in it both <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Goats;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.14.</note> to a <hi>Great Houſe,</hi> wherein <hi>are not only Veſſels of Gold and of Silver,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.32, 33.</note> 
               <hi>but alſo of Wood and of Earth; and ſome to Honour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>and ſome to Diſhonour:</hi> Wherefore we may not pretend to ſeparate our ſelves from all thoſe that do immoral things; for then, as the Apoſtle ſays, <hi>We
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55533:11"/>muſt needs go out of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 5.10.</note> Nor if Men do ſuch things, muſt they thereupon be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Schiſmaticks, or to have departed from the outward Communion of the Church? But if they make them Terms of Communion, or perſiſt ſo long in them, as to give a juſt occaſion of Church-Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures upon them, and wilfully remain under thoſe Cenſures.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, by <hi>Agenda,</hi> or Morals, I would not be underſtood, to mean that only which is obligatory in its own nature, but that alſo which obligeth on the account of Divine Inſtitution, as the Sacraments; by diminiſhing from which, or adding to them, Men break the Unity of the Church of God, and make it unlawful for others to joyn with them. They treſpaſs indeed againſt Faith and Morals alſo, taking away from Men the Seals of God's Covenant, the Tokens of his Favour, the Pawns and Pledges of the Performance of his Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, appointed by himſelf for the quicken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Faith, and ſacrilegiouſly robbing God of the principal and moſt memora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Part of his Worſhip, whereby we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55533:12"/>in moſt Solemn Manner, a Belief of his Promiſes, and vow Obedience to his Commands, whereby we put on the Badges and diſtinguiſhing Marks of our Chriſtian Calling. Theſe are therefore the ſtricteſt and higheſt Bands of Union, from which St. <hi>Paul</hi> in divers places infers the Unity of the Church: <hi>We being many, are one Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and one Bread; for we are all partakers of that one Bread,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.17. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>By one Spirit we are all baptized in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one Body, whether we be Jews or Gentiles, whether we be Bond or Free, and have all been made to drink into one Spirit,</hi> I Cor. 12.13.</p>
            <p>And both theſe kinds of Schiſm; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch as are conſtituted by profeſſing Errors in Faith or Morals, do imply Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie alſo, and may be called by either Name, according to our different Conſideration of them; as they do imply falſe Doctrine in Matters neceſſary to Salvation, obſtinately perſiſted in, Hereſie; as the are accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panyed with Separation from the Church, or do give a juſt Cauſe of Separation, Schiſm. <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Schiſm</hi> are ſeldom
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55533:12"/>long aſunder. There are few Hereticks but will endeavour by ſeparate Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations to propagate their Hereſie; or Schiſmaticks, but will frame to themſeves ſome New Doctrine, the better to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their Separation from the Church, as <note n="*" place="margin">On. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.</note> St. <hi>Jerom</hi> obſerved. The Apoſtle ſeems to uſe both theſe Words in the ſame Senſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.18, 19. <hi>I hear that there be Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> (the Word is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,) <hi>among you; and I partly believe it, for there muſt be alſo Hereſies among you,</hi> &amp;c, And certainly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Heretick, openly profeſſing and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his Hereſie, whether he is able to get a ſeparate Congregation or not, may be called a Schiſmatick; and a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick perſiſting in his Schiſm, will be very apt to fall into Hereſie, according to the forecited Paſſage of St. <hi>Jerom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Whole Churches, as well as ſingle Perſons, may incur the Guilt of Schiſm, by their differences about Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſometimes as to the <hi>Species</hi> or kind of Government, and ſometimes as to the manner of exerciſing it.</p>
            <p>Sometimes by a different <hi>Species</hi> or kind
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55533:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Government: As for Inſtance; When they do recede from Epiſcopacy, and break wilfully the Line of Apoſtolical Succeſſion: For in ſo doing, they cauſe probably great Diſorders within themſelves, and in other Churches alſo, by looſing the Bands of Union among themſelves, and hindering good Correſpondence with other Churches, by taking away the chief Pillars and Suppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that Correſpondence, and tacitly diſappointing their ſort of Government, tempting ſome of them to diſlike it, and to endeavour a Change for that which is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to prove much worſe inſtead of it, as on many other accounts ſo particularly, becauſe it hath not the Examples of the beſt and pureſt Ages to maintain it. But tho' Churches may ſometimes be Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical on this account, yet they are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſo in this Caſe: For there may be a juſt Cauſe of breaking off that outward Succeſſion, where the Profeſſion of the true Chriſtian Faith, and of good Morals, muſt be otherwiſe utterly wanting; the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of which, is declared in the Holy Scriptures neceſſary to Salvation, not the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:55533:13"/>manner of Government ſo declared; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, this cannot be equally neceſſary to all People. This, in caſe of a general Corruption, or ſometimes on the Account of the Members of the Church being di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed abroad, perhaps cannot be had: And muſt Men Continue in ſuch Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for fear of breaking off Succeſſion? Or fall into a ſtate of Damnation, for not being able to preſerve it? What Uncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties will ſome Mens Doctrine make all the Advantages we can receive from Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and finally our Salvation to depend upon? Sometimes on the Goodneſs of a a King's, ſometimes of a Biſhop's Title, and ſometimes on the Regularity of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. How unreaſonably are Men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, whom God hath not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and declared to be in the ſtate of thoſe that never heard of Chriſt, even al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they do perform all the Goſpel Conditions? Only becauſe they have not among them a certain Order, which is not abſolutely neceſſary to the Being, <note n="*" place="margin">— What hath periſhed of the Outward From or Body of Government, being loſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any fault or guilt of theirs, (their Infelicity, which they could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, and not their Crime voluntarily brought upon themſelves:) This ſure will never be look'd on by God as any dangerous want of Order, or as that which ſhall be any way chargeable up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der is required to the Well-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary abſolutely to the Being of a Church; and orderleſs or ſecret Society of Brethren, may be a Church ſtill, as any number of Converts in a City, before the Apoſtle, which was gone to ſome other City, had yet placed any Governour over them. Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi>'s <hi>Second Defence of the Treatiſe of Schiſm,</hi> Ch. 6. S. 11.</note> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55533:14"/>to the Well-being of the Church. It is no where commanded, although it ſeems indeed to the approved of by our bleſſed Saviour in the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rev. ch. 2.</note>, and is plainly enough made out to have been inſtituted by the Apoſtles, and hath been found by Experience a very ſtrong Band of Union, in reſpect of the Univerſal Church, and particular ones too, where it hath had its juſt Authority: Not but that the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in ſome places hath failed, or been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted, (I do not except the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, which doth boaſt ſo much of it) and may fail again; or we may depart from it when it cannot conſiſt with Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of true Faith and good Morals, without an utter and irrecoverable loſs of the Advantages of the Chriſtian Religion, the Church of Chriſt, or the ordinary hopes of Salvation. And although no Man ought to aſſume to himſelf a Power of Governing the Church of God, but ſtay till it is regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly conferr'd upon him; yet, where there is a general Deficiency and Apoſtacy from the Profeſſion of the true Faith and ſound Morals, and they who are to confer this
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:55533:14"/>Right, are themſelves corrupted alſo, and will not give this Power to any that are willing to reform it; in ſuch extraordinary caſes of general Apoſtacy, (which, how far it may poſſibly reach, I will not here diſpute) Perſons, Prieſts at leaſt, who have Gifts and Abilities for it, have a ſufficient <hi>Call</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſe themſelves, and are not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but highly commended for making uſe of it.</p>
            <p>Sometimes again, there may be a Schiſm made by the ill Exerciſe of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; by a Churches refuſing to hold Communion with the reſt, or unjuſtly cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring and excommunicating them, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeying General Councils, the Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of the whole Church, in matters which they have a lawful Power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; by uſurping too great Authority over the reſt; by aſſuming the Name of Catholick to it ſelf, in oppoſition to all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches; by making ſuch unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Terms of Communion, as that others ſhall not be able to communicate with it; by encouraging and upholding Perſons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, or deſervedly declared Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55533:15"/>by other Churches; by wilfully continuing in Faults, and under juſt Excommunication incurred thereupon; by refuſing to keep friendly Correſpondence with other Churches, as in Communicato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Letters, (which are in order to the well governing of the Church) and the like.</p>
            <p>And it is about the Exerciſe of Church-Government, that Schiſm is generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant: All Schiſms of particular Members of the Church, conſidered as diſtinct from Hereſies, are about Church-Government; and commonly about the Exerciſe of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing occaſioned either,
<list>
                  <item>1. By Superiors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending for Power; or,</item>
                  <item>2. Miſemploying their Power; or,</item>
                  <item>3. By Inferiors Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Power.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By Superiors, Civil or Eccleſiaſtical, contending for Power: The Civil Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors uſurping that which belongs to the Eccleſiaſtical, or the Eccleſiaſtical that which belongs to the Civil, or the Eccleſiaſtical Governors contending with one another; For the Contention of Civil Governors, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered only as ſuch, <hi>i. e.</hi> about their own Rights and Titles, will not conſtitute a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55533:15"/>Schiſm, nor give a juſt occaſion for a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration; although ſome have lately, as it ſeems, taken occaſion to make a Schiſm on the account thereof, whoſe Principles are partly conſidered in that which went before, and will be farther in that which follows, according as they ſhall be found under their proper Heads.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It may be committed by Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, invading the Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Eccleſiaſtical: For although it be true, that every one of the Clergy is ſubject to the Civil Governors; I mean, to that one or more Perſons in whom the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Power is lodged: Yet there are ſome parts of their Office, which no King or Prince can aſſume to himſelf; as The Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Keys, the Power of Ordination, of adminiſtring the Sacraments, of officia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting as Prieſts in the Publick Worſhip of God, and other ſuch like; which if they undertake without being lawfully called thereunto of God, they are guilty (among other ſins) of the ſin of Schiſm; and we may ſay unto them, as the Prieſts did to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55533:16"/>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> when he went to burn Incenſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Altar; <hi>It appertaineth not unto thee,</hi> Uzziah, <hi>to burn Incenſe unto the Lord, but to the Prieſts the Sons of</hi> Aaron, <hi>that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated to burn incenſe,</hi> 2 Cor. 26.18.</p>
            <p n="2">II. There is a Schiſm made when Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Governors deny the Authority of the Supreme Civil Powers; for they have the care of the Church alſo, being <hi>Cuſtodes utriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> Tabulae,</hi> and appointed to be <hi>nurſing Fathers</hi> of the Church. Our Obligation to every Human Law is derived from the Divine; and ſeeing Religion is the ſupport of all Government, and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of all Juſtice <note n="*" place="margin">Quod in Religionem Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinam committitur in om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium fertur injuriam, <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> de Hereticis.</hi>
               </note> and Peace, it cannot but belong to their care. They therefore that ſhall deny them that Power, which is annexed to their Imperial Dignity; To reform Abuſes in the Worſhip of God, and in the Clergy; to conſtitute Biſhops and Paſtors; on occaſion, to depoſe or deprive them; to call together and to preſide in Councils; to diſpenſe with their Canons, to reſcind or alter them as they ſee a juſt occaſion: All
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55533:16"/>which things Chriſtian Kings have done, and that upon good grounds. If theſe are indeed the Powers of the Sovereign, as it may be proved <note n="†" place="margin">You may ſee all this very well proved in <hi>Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, de imperio Summarum Poteſtatum circa Sacra.</hi> And good part of it is owned by the Author of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Communion,</hi> p. 26, 27.29. and elſewhere.</note> they are, then, they who deny them theſe Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and aſſume the ſame to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, are Schiſmaticks: Such are therefore the Papiſts, who by virtue of their <hi>Ordination,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be gotten out of the power of Princes, and independent on them; yea, to be above them, and to go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern them <hi>in temporalibus in ordine ad ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituale bonum,</hi> 
               <note n="‖" place="margin">Bellarminus de Rom. Pont, <hi>lib. 5. cap. 6.</hi> Papa potest mutare regna, &amp; uni auferre, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> alteri conferre, tanquam ſummus Princeps ſpiritualis, ſi id neceſſarium ſit ad anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſalutem. <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> by which Claim they ſhew the unreaſonableneſs of all the reſt, in effect confeſſing that to the right management of the Spiritual, there is a neceſſity of an over-ruling Temporal Power, which they would therefore get unto themſelves.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Eccleſiaſtical Governors become Schiſmaticks, by contending for Power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves: As for Example; When one Biſhop lays claim to the Dioceſe of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55533:17"/>another, ſetting up himſelf, or ſuffering others to ſet him up an Anti-Biſhop, <hi>erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Altar againſt Altar,</hi> according to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Phraſe. And in ſome Elections in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it hath been difficult to know who was the Anti Biſhop; and the Emperor upon ſuch an occaſion, hath cauſed <note n="†" place="margin">The Caſe of <hi>Bonifacius</hi> and <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lius,</hi> Baron. Ann. 419. §. 15.</note> both of the Contenders to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of the City; yea, after having called a Synod <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <p>Henricus Secundus in italiam cum magno exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu veniens, habitâ Synedo, cum Benedictum nonum, Sylveſtrum tertium Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſextum tanquam tria teterrima menſtra abdicare ſe inagiſtratu coegiſſet, Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degerum Bambergenſem-E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopum, cui Clementi ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo appellatio fuit Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficem creat. <hi>Platina de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Pontif. 155. Pont.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Clemens Secundus, Synde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerus antea vocatus, Bam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergenſis Epiſcopus in Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Pontifex creatur, annu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ente Henrico Secundo vel impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ante, &amp;. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e potius. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m 156. Pont.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note>, he hath depoſed at one time three, that have pretended a Right to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, and created a fourth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of them, to preſerve the Peace of the Church. But there is not always the ſame difficulty to know who is the true Biſhop: As for inſtance;</p>
            <p>If a Biſhop reſigns or gives up his Dioceſe, and after the vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy thereof another be put in his room, he cannot afterwards come back and lay claim to a Dioceſe ſo given up, any more than to one that he never preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded over at all: And therefore, in that caſe it is plain enough, that he is the Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55533:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>or the Anti-Biſhop, that comes to put in any ſuch claim.</p>
            <p>And a Biſhop is under the ſame Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, who is put out of his Dioceſe by ſufficient Authority, and is under the ſame guilt of Schiſm, if he comes to make a ſecond claim to the ſame Dioceſe. For it is very clear, that if he be deprived by a ſufficient Power, he is in the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as if he never had been their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop. Such an one therefore, who has been ſo deprived, if he ſhall return and ſay to the People; I am your true Paſtor ſtill; you ought to obey, not this Man that hath ſucceeded, but me; He is juſtly to be eſteemed a Schiſmatick, and ſo are conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently all they that do defend him, and adhere to him.</p>
            <p>I know there have been two things urged, and are chiefly inſiſted upon, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of a Separation of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; 1. <note n="*" place="margin">This is the Summ of what is objected in the firſt Part of <hi>Chriſtian Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</hi>
               </note> That Biſhops, though deprived to Temporalities, are not diveſted of their Spiritual Power; that it is their Duty, expreſs'd by their Titles of <hi>Watchmen, Meſſengers, Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:55533:18"/>&amp;c. in holy Scripture to make uſe of that their Power, in order to the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Immoralities; which accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Opinion of thoſe who hold the preſent King to be only King <hi>de facto,</hi> and the other to be King <hi>de jure</hi> (whom they ſuppoſe to be the major part) muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily, as they ſay, follow, by praying for the King <hi>de facto,</hi> the unjuſt Poſſeſſor, as they underſtand it, againſt the King <hi>de jure,</hi> the rightful King, in the publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, eſpecially on the more ſolemn days of Faſting, Thankſgiving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. They (having <note n="*" place="margin">Chriſtian Communion, <hi>pag. 8.</hi>
               </note> profeſſedly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Queſtion about the King's Title) do urge, that the Depriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Temporalities merely by a <note n="‖" place="margin">This objected in the Second Part.</note> Lay-power is invalid. <note n="†" place="margin">This is inferred from the fomer Principles in the Third Part.</note> Therefore the old Biſhops retain ſtill their Right, the others are Anti-Biſhops and Schiſmaticks that are ſet up againſt them.</p>
            <p>As to the Firſt of theſe Objections, I anſwer, 1. That the Author who makes it, ſeems to have miſunderſtood the Treatiſe called <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of a new Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55533:18"/>on the account of the Oaths, &amp;c.</hi> which he quotes in divers places and deſervedly commends. Wherefore I ſhall repeat ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing out of it. <hi>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper is one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of a new Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pag. 30.</note> 
               <hi>who comes in by Force, and continues by Force. A King</hi> de jure <hi>is one, who comes in by li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal Deſcent, as next Heir, and whoſe Right is owned and Recognized by the Eſtates of the Realm. A King</hi> de facto <hi>is one, who comes in by conſent of the Nation, but not by virtue of an</hi> immediate Hereditary Right; <hi>but to ſuch a one being owned and received by the Eſtates of the Realm, the Law of</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>as far as I can ſee, requires an Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then a King <hi>de facto</hi> doth not ſignifie an unjuſt Poſſeſſor, for he is King <hi>jure op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo;</hi> By ſuch a Right as ſuperſedes the bare right of Inheritance not recognized by the Eſtates of the Realm; By ſuch a Right as all the Laws which make our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance due to a King <hi>de facto</hi> do confirm, by ſuch a Right as implies ſometimes, and particularly in the preſent Caſe, an expreſs and free Conſent of the People by their Repreſentatives, which is better than a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55533:19"/>Conſent implied in Preſcription, (which in theſe days is the only thing that can make Succeſſion a good Title, conſidered as diſtinct from other Titles) or a forced Conſent, <hi>i. e.</hi> Conſent ſubſequent upon Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, which only doth make Conqueſt a good Title.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for any other meaning of <hi>a King de facto,</hi> I ſhall not concern my ſelf with it, but only take notice, that, whether Men call the preſent King, King <hi>de facto,</hi> or <hi>de jure,</hi> if they hold him to be their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to whom Allegiance is due (which can never be due from the ſame Perſon to two oppoſite Kings at once,) the Prayers for his Preſervation, Victory over his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do not contain any Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities but only that which is their bounden Duty, and that which is implyed if we ſhould uſe no other than the Apoſtles own words, Praying, <hi>For Kings, and for all that are in Authority;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>that we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty.</hi> Nor is then the uſing, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſuch Prayers on days by their Superiors appointed for ſolemn Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55533:19"/>rather to be eſteemed an Immora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But if Men ſhould uſe thoſe Prayers againſt their Conſciences, and profeſs they did ſo, (which it is to be hoped few or none do) or if they ſhould be guilty of other open and acknowledg'd Immorali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, muſt He that is not Biſhop of the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe come thither to reform them? Then for the Extirpation of Immoralities, which are to be found more or leſs in every Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſe, any Biſhop might invade the Dioceſe of another, ſaying he came to take away Immoralities, to teach Men their duty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though the Commiſſion of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when <hi>the Labourers</hi> were few, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite over all the World, and that of Biſhops and Paſtors is ſo in ſome ſort now, in regard they are according to their Places and Stations to give aſſiſtance to and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Edification of the whole Church of Chriſt, and are in that ſenſe Biſhops over all the Church; yet they are to be under certain Orders and Rules and within bounds, ſuch as may be conſiſtent with the good Government and Peace of the Church; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55533:20"/>not to make their Dioceſes as large as they pleaſe, or go <note n="a" place="margin">A <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> diſorderly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their own Precincts or proper Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtricts. Whence it was juſtly forbidden (if not by expreſs <note n="b" place="margin">Act. 20.28. Tit. 1.5.</note> Scripture, as ſome think yet) by the Canons called <note n="c" place="margin">Can. Apoſt. 14.35.</note> Apoſtolical, by the two firſt General <note n="d" place="margin">Conc. Nic. Can. 6, 7.8. Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop. Can. 2.</note> Councils, by the Council of <hi>Antioch</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Can. 13.22.</note>, and by the Imperial Laws, <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 14 <hi>&amp;</hi> l. 36. C. de Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis, &amp; Clericis.</note>, that one Biſhop ſhould <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſee <hi>Zonaras.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Invade</hi> the Dioceſe of another; whereby in underſtood doing the Epiſcopal Offices therein with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <note n="h" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> conſent of the Biſhop of the Place; when he is not <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>mon in Can. 2. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop.</note> gone off, or deprived; without being appointed <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by other Biſhops ſo to do; not being in <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Barbarous Nations where Biſhops and Paſtors are wanting. Without ſome of which Reaſons ſpecified and excepted by the Councils prohibiting them, no Man therefore ought to return back to officiate in a Dioceſe of which he is deprived, notwithſtanding any pretence of Immoralities.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and Laſtly, Schiſm is a great Immorality, and hath many others evident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſequent upon it, ſo that if by ſuch proceedings they make a Schiſm (the juſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55533:20"/>Imputation whereof I know not how they can avoid) then inſtead of bringing Men out of, they bring them into Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and therefore by their Titles of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, Watchmen, &amp;c.</hi> they are obliged not to return.</p>
            <p>It may be, 'twill be ſaid that theſe Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſes are their own, and that they come to recover their own Rights. But
<list>
                  <item>1. If theſe were indeed their Rights, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not by thus returning hope to recover them, neither are they capable by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Eſtabliſhment of having them, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the others ſhould be willing to reſign or deliver the Dioceſes up to them.</item>
                  <item>2. Where the fore-mentioned Cauſe is wanting or inſufficient, <hi>viz.</hi> that of ill Morals, this latter, of Right, by a true lover of Peace will be parted with of Courſe.</item>
               </list>
               <note place="margin">John 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>The good Shepherd giveth his life for the Sheep,</hi> much more is he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to part with the profits of his Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Office to do them good. And as the true Mother of the Child, in the Caſe brought before <hi>Solomon,</hi> would rather ſuffer her Child to go to another Woman
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55533:21"/>then let it be divided: So will a true Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor, rather ſuffer his Flock to go to any other Orthodox Biſhop, than let it be crumbled and broken into Factions on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the ſake of him. The pretended Mother of that Child might have made her excuſe with the Schiſmaticks of our days, that ſhe had rather her Child ſhould be cut in pieces, than guilty of an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality in Honouring a falſe Mother, and witholding due Honour from the true One. And yet ſhe that had not that Scruple was the beſt Woman, and the true Mother of the Child as <hi>Solomon</hi> judged; and the Scripture approves his Judgment. And this would be ſuch an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Immorality as the Authors of theſe late Books of Schiſm talk of in paying Allegiance to one whom Men might mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake to be their King. But they wave the queſtion about the King's Title, as I ſaid before, and inſiſt on the invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of a <hi>Lay-deprivation</hi> the next thing to be conſidered; by way of anſwer to the ſecond Objection.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:55533:21"/>
            <p>This Deprivation does not take away the Power conferr'd on them in Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but only of having ſuch and ſuch Dioceſes or parts of the Kingdom to officiate in; which why the Supreme Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Power, whether lodged in one or more Men, ſhould not be ſufficient to do, is altogether unintelligible. The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution or diviſion of a Country into ſo many <hi>Dioceſes</hi> is not <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> but depends on the diſcretion and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the chief Governors of the Church, <hi>i. e.</hi> in a Chriſtian Country, of the Supreme Legiſlative Power; to the Preſervation whereof it is neceſſary to have them well marked out and fixed, and to the well-being of the Republick. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops are Subjects, and Kings may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Allegiance of them; and in caſe of refuſal, if they have the whole Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlative Power, they may forbid them living in any part of their Dominions. Such Power is neceſſarily annexed to, or rather implied in the Imperial Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; from which our bleſſed Saviour by his Goſpel detracted nothing, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55533:22"/>to uphold his Diſciples or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles againſt it; for his <hi>Kingdom</hi> was <hi>not of this World.</hi> And though the Church did ſubſiſt at firſt without the aſſiſtance of Heathen Emperors, yet Kings, when they embraced the true Faith, became Members of the Church as well as any other Believers, and are therefore as much obliged to act according to the Station wherein they are placed: As did the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Kings notwithſtanding that the Church, in <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> did ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without them; and as did the firſt and beſt of Chriſtian Emperors; And among the reſt of thoſe Powers, that of depriving Biſhops hath been one. And this Power hath been exerciſed here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, with the Approbation of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and conſonantly to the Articles, Homilies and Canons there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And among the Reaſons of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation the not acknowledging the Kings Supremacy in Eccleſiaſtical Cauſes was none of the leaſt; which yet is not ſo much as to deny his Civil Authority alſo, which is the preſent <note n="*" place="margin">See the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of their Majeſties Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to fill the Sees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Caſe. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55533:22"/>if we conſider the Supreme Power only as having ſo much Authority as is abſolutely neceſſary to preſerve the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Government, and to ſecure the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace of the Kingdom, we muſt own that it can judge alſo, what ſhall be reaſonable Security of any Subjects being true to the Government; and that Eccleſiaſtical Perſons as well as others, for want of ſuch Security given, may be deprived of places of truſt, or places where they may have conſiderable influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence on the People, leaſt they ſhould pervert them to diſaffection.<note place="margin">Cujus rei faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis eſt probatio &amp;c. <hi>Grotius</hi> De Imperio Summar. Tot. circa Sacra, Cap. 10. § 33.</note> Hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows a Power of removing Biſhops from their Sees upon ſuch occaſions; which that it belongs to the Sovereign, <hi>Grotius</hi> thinks is a very eaſy matter to prove. For he that hath power to baniſh a Man out of all parts of the Country or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, hath by <note n="*" place="margin">Hoc enim illi ineſt; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cujus totum eſt in Poteſtate, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus in Poteſtate pars non eſſe non potest. <hi>Idem ibid.</hi>
               </note> Conſequence a Power of forbidding him to exerciſe there the Epiſcopal Office. This he can do as the ſame <hi>Grotius</hi> obſerves, not only by way of Puniſhment, but alſo by way of Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he finds the People tumultuous
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55533:23"/>on the account of any Paſtor, though without the Paſtor's fault.</p>
            <p>And ſuch Deprivation may be made not only without, but even againſt the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of a <hi>Synod;</hi> of whom Kings are ſo far from being obliged to ask the queſtion, whether they ſhall have their Subjects Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance or no; that they are rather obliged, eſpecially here in <hi>England,</hi> not to ask or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of them; becauſe it is a Violation of of the Laws of the Land, and an injury done to the proper Judges of Allegiance. And although in Caſes of Hereſy or Schiſm (when there are matters of difficulty to be decided) it is very fit and proper, and agreeable to the moſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and uſual practice of the Church to call <hi>Synods;</hi> Yet even in thoſe Caſes they are to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened only at the Sovereign's <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Socr. Proaem. lib. 5. <hi>Doce — quis Imperator hane Synodum juſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                        <desc>••…</desc>
                     </gap> Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri?</hi> Hieron. Apolog. adv. Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. 2.</note> appointment, and when they are come together, they are all of them under the ſame Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Obedience to the Civil Power, as they were ſingly before; obliged to the ſame Duties, and liable to the ſame
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55533:23"/>Penalties upon refuſal of them. How then can this be a matter of Eccleſiaſtical Cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance, or how can it belong to them to determine it?</p>
            <p>Examples of Emperors depoſing Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops without as well as with a <hi>Synod</hi> are many, and that even in the Caſe of <hi>Hereſy,</hi> which doth moſt properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the determination of a <hi>Synod,</hi> and which they are beſt able to judge of; not but that in plain Caſes, or Caſes before ſufficiently declared Hereſy, this may be done without them, even as Kings in the Old-Teſtament, brake down the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, deſtroyed the high Places, and put down the Idolatrous Prieſts by their own Authority; which Kings under the New-Teſtament having the entire Legiſlative Power, do not come ſhort of. Thus Chriſtian Emperors have depoſed Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, and their Power to do ſo ſeems an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently to have been generally acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged on all hands. All Parties ſeem to have been ſenſible thereof. Sometimes the Emperor threatned to depoſe them, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55533:24"/>ſometimes put it in Execution, without any ones gain-ſaying. To him Biſhops brought their <note n="a" place="margin">Theodorit, lib. 5. c. 23.</note> Complaints againſt ſuch other Biſhops as they deſired to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; Him they ſometimes <note n="b" place="margin">Leo. 1. Ep. 99.</note> praiſed for uſing this Power; His Power they <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Flavianus</hi> in Theodor. loco citato.</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, though againſt themſelves; In his Sentence, though ſometimes unjuſt, they acquieſced <note n="d" place="margin">Socrat. lib. 2. c. 12.</note>. And this is more than to depoſe them on the account of State-Crimes, or for default of Allegiance. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; As this is agreeable to Antient Practiſe, ſo it is the conſtant and concurrent Senſe of all the old Reformers, and till of late it hath been denyed, I think, by none but Papiſts, and ſome of the worſt and maddeſt of Enthuſiaſts.</p>
            <p>And thus Men may become guilty of Schiſm by contending for Power. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may alſo diſcern, how Perſons in other Relations, according as they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be concerned in ſome of theſe Circumſtances, may become guilty of the ſame fault.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:55533:24"/>
            <p n="2">2. They may be Schiſmaticks by miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imploying their Power, and ſo cutting themſelves off from thoſe that are under them. For there is no Place ſo high as to make a Man incapable of this fault. Nor may Inferiors only be guilty of it in reſpect of their Superiors, or Superiors in reſpect of one another, but Superiors in reſpect of their Inferiors alſo. <hi>The Head</hi> may <hi>ſay to the Feet, I have no need of you,</hi> as well as the <hi>Feet to the Head, we have no need of thee.</hi> Wherefore the Supreme Civil Powers, if they ſhall ſet up and pull down Perſons at pleaſure, encouraging, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, promoting Schiſmaticks, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing or highly diſcouraging thoſe that are Orthodox: Eccleſiaſtical Governors, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Paſtors, if they ſhall do the like; if they ſhall refuſe to communicate with their Flock, unjuſtly excommunicate them, forbid them Communion in expreſs Terms, or by Conſequence exclude them by unjuſt Impoſitions and unreaſonable Terms of Communion, are guilty of Schiſm.</p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:55533:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>3ly.</hi> Men are Schiſmaticks by diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Power, and that this may belong in ſome ſort to any Member of the Church,<note place="margin">Pag. 13.</note> yea, or to any particular Church, hath been obſerved already; alſo that the Common People may have a ſhare in and partake of the guilt of Schiſm in moſt of the Caſes already mentioned, is not to be doubted; but I am taking notice only of what hath been as yet omitted, and comes neareſt to being peculiar to the Common People. And that is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience to their Lawful Governors in Spiritual Matters. Yet not all Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is Schiſmatical, (for then every Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor of Canons might be called a Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick) but ſuch as is <hi>Cum Rebellione qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> as the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> 22. Q. 39. Art. 1. ad Zum.</note> School-men expreſs it; when Men deſign thereby to ſignify openly deſert them,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.3.</note> and <hi>heap to themſelves Teachers after their own Luſts, having itching Ears;</hi> when they diſown and diſclaim their Authority; when they preſume to invade the Biſhops, Prieſts or Deacons Office without being lawfully called, <hi>climbing</hi> into the <hi>Sheepfold an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other way,</hi> inſtead of <hi>entring in at the Door;</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:55533:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>when they refuſe to Communicate on reaſonable Terms, or ſeparate themſelves becauſe they will not conform in Publick Aſſemblies to your Superiors Injunctions as to Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which laſt I ſee not how they can excuſe from Schiſm, except in two Caſes only. 1. That the Things commanded and appointed by them are unlawful in themſelves; in which Caſe, without all queſtion, it is their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to diſobey them, and rather to ſeparate from them, than to comply and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with them in that which is ſinful. Or <hi>2ly.</hi> If they be not unlawful in their own Nature, but indifferent, as being no where forbidden; yet if they are unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in reſpect of ſome Circumſtances, as if they ſhould be ſo many and ſo extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inconvenient, as to hinder Men in their chief deſign of Worſhipping God in their Aſſemblies, and Men have no other way of getting themſelves relieved. But this, ſome Improprieties of Speech, or inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant Ceremonies, if not too many and frequent, can never hinder. Yea, a few of them need not take off the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55533:26"/>of Devotion in Men of Charity or Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Moreover if ſuch excuſes as theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> having better words, more ſignificant Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, or none at all, were of any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, they never would be wanting, nor would there be a poſſibility of keeping Order, Unity, or Peace in any Church whatſoever. Our bleſſed Saviour, beſide his Precepts of Love and Charity, hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided no means to prevent ſuch Cavels as theſe are, neither is it poſſible. Mens Fancies never did, never can agree in all theſe Particulars; nor can any one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps at all times agree with himſelf. And therefore I ſhall not here ſpend any more time upon them.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid, it appears, that there are ways, and thoſe more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps than I have yet enumerated or can reckon up, whereby Men may become guilty of Schiſm in all Eſtates and Conditions. Whence it is not without cauſe that the Fathers, when they are ſpeaking about Schiſm, do repreſent it
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55533:26"/>ſo <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>S Ignatii Epiſt. ad Philadelph. c. 7. It is called</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Clement. Ep. ad Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth 1. cap. 47.</hi>
                  <p>Epiſcopatum autem tenere non poſſet etiamſi Epiſcopus prius factus, a Coepiſcopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuorum corpore &amp; ab Eccleſiae unitate deſciſceret. <hi>Cypr. Ep. 55.</hi> Qui ſe ab Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae vinculo at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> a Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotum Collegio ſeparat Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi nec poteſtatem potest habere, nec honorem, <hi>Id. ibid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>An eſſe ſibi cum Chriſto videtur qui adverſus Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes Chriſti facit? qui ſe a Cleri e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s &amp; plebis Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate diſcernit. <hi>Id. De unitat. Eccleſiae Ed. Oxon. p. 116.</hi> — Plebs obſequens praeceptis Dominicis, &amp; Deum metu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, a peccatore praepoſito ſeparare ſe debet, nec ſe ad Sacrilegi Sacerdotis ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia miſcere, &amp;c. <hi>Id. Ep. 67. Ed. Oxon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> variouſly, ſometimes as a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the Biſhop, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the Prieſts, ſometimes from the Deacons, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times from the common People; as doth S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> himſelf. Whence we may ſee how little weight there is in that Saving common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly quoted out of his 66. Epiſt. <hi>Scire debes Epiſcopum in Eccleſia eſſe &amp; Eccleſiam in Epiſcopo, &amp; ſi qui cum Epiſcopo non ſint in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia non eſſe;</hi> as to the uſes which have been lately made of it.</p>
            <p>And in all the fore-mentioned Caſes, the Schiſm proceeds from one or more Members, not hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a due care and concern for the reſt, or from not having an equal Care according to their reſpective States and Conditions. And therefore the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in the place before quoted, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.25. doth intimate that there would be <hi>no Schiſm in the Body,</hi> if all the Members did take <hi>the ſame care one for another.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:55533:27"/>
            <p>Laſtly, We may obſerve, that every particular Schiſm is an injury to and a Schiſm in reſpect of the whole Church; as every diviſion of any one Member of the Body is by conſequence againſt the whole Body; which is not ſound, compleat, and intire, except it be ſo in every particular Member of it, or if but one of the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers is broken. Therefore, as our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſays concerning the doing or denying any charitable Act,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.40, 45</note> 
               <hi>Inſomuch as you did, or did it not to one of the leaſt of theſe, you did or did it not unto me:</hi> So we may ſay, where a Schiſm is made in any particular Church; In as much as you have made a Diviſion in this particular Church, you have ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated your ſelves from Chriſt the Head, and made a Rent in the whole Body.</p>
            <p>But perhaps Men would not be ſo apt of themſelves, or ſo eaſily prevailed upon by others to Separate themſelves from their Brethren, did they duly conſider, how great a Crime, of how ill and dangerous conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence to the Church in general, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and others, this of Schiſm is, which therefore I ſhall take ſome Conſideration
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55533:27"/>of; and it is the ſecond thing I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſpeak to: Wherein I do not deſign to make Reflections on any one Party more than another, but only to conſider the nature of this Sin indifferent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to whomſoever it may belong.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who, as I obſerved before, uſeth Hereſy and Schiſm promiſcuouſly, as did alſo the Primitive Chriſtians for ſome time after him,<note place="margin">Gal. 5.20. 1 Cor. 3.3, 4</note> reckons it among the <hi>works of the Fleſh.</hi> Whereby he ſignifies that it is not commonly on a bare Miſtake, or Miſapprehenſion of Things, nor out of Zeal for Religion; but upon ſome world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Deſigns and Intereſts, that Men do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come guilty of it. But whatever the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign may be, a very dangerous and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious thing it is.</p>
            <p>Unity is the Strength of all Societies, Diviſion the Weakneſs and Infirmity of them. There is no readier way to deſtroy a Church then to divide it. <hi>Every King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom divided againſt it ſelf is brought to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and a Houſe divided againſt a Houſe falleth.</hi> Wherefore Schiſm lays the <hi>Axe to the root</hi> of that Church wherein it is bred,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55533:28"/>and tends to the utter Ruin and Subverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, firſt of it; next, if it be in a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Church, of the Proteſtant Religion, which it hereby lays open to powerful Adverſaries; and laſt of all of Chriſtianity it ſelf. Every particular Schiſm in ſome ſort reacheth the Univerſal Church, as I have already ſhewn. So it is againſt the Goſpel and againſt Chriſt;<note place="margin">Vide. Gregor. Tholoſ. Syn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tag. jur. Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi. lib. 33. cap. 11. § 1.</note> and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Crimen laeſae Majeſtatis Divinae,</hi> as ſome do ſtile it.</p>
            <p>It is againſt the deſign of our Saviour's coming into the World; who came <hi>to make Peace,</hi> not only between God and Man, but alſo amongſt Men. He gave the ſtricteſt Commands about it; He contrived the firmeſt Bands to maintain it. Schiſm violates theſe Precepts, fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates this Deſign, breaketh theſe Bands, makes our Saviour's Paſſion vain, and the Croſs of Chriſt to be of none effect. It makes the Evangelical Writings vain; for the Goſpel was written to that intent which the Schiſmatick diſappointeth. St. <hi>John</hi> ſays,<note place="margin">1 John 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>That which we have heard and ſeen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we unto you that ye, may have fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55533:28"/>with us, and truly our Fellowſhip is with the Father and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A good Shepherd gathers the Sheep together; the Schiſmatick makes it his buſineſs to ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them.</p>
            <p>It gives Scandal to thoſe that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. The Diviſions of Chriſtians in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral do give offence unto the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> and make the <hi>name of God Blaſphem'd among the Gentiles,</hi> and the Diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Proteſtants to make our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Blaſphemed amongſt the Papiſts. It cauſeth Atheiſm and Infidelity, when each part ſays there is no Salvation to be had in the contrary Part; diſſolute Perſons perſwade themſelves that there is none in either. And while ſome Men are crying, <hi>Lo here is Chriſt,</hi> and others, <hi>Lo he is there,</hi> ſuch as might otherwiſe have a Mind to enter into the Church know not whither to come.</p>
            <p>It makes all Virtues in general not to thrive ſo well, in that Church where there are Diviſions; it diſturbeth that <hi>Joy</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> which are the <hi>Fruites of the</hi> Holy <hi>Spirit</hi> of God; it takes off much from that comfort in Chriſt, which ſhould be the lot of every Pious and devout Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:55533:29"/>Whence there is not only great Vehemence of Paſſion, but admirable ſoundneſs of Reaſon in that earneſt Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Apoſtle to Unity,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>If there be any Conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of Love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit, if any Bowels and Mercies; fulfil ye my Joy, that ye be like minded, having the ſame Love, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one Accord, of one Mind.</hi> Whence<note n="*" place="margin">St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> in divers places.</note> ſome have called it <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> not only becauſe it is a Violation of Divine Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Uſurpation of Sacred Offices, but becauſe it ſeems to be far greater rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery to deprive the Church of the benefit of all theſe things, then to take the Silver or Gold out of the Temple.</p>
            <p>It ſhews want of Charity or Love, as of God ſo alſo of our Brethren, on ſuch eaſy terms to divide our ſelves from them; too hardly to Judge them; too highly to Eſteem our ſelves; too little to bear with them; to be too ready to grieve them; not to have compaſſion on their Neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Wants in Spiritual matters; not to be willing to give them our aſſiſtance as Members of the ſame Body ſhould do
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55533:29"/>to one another. Wherefore the Apoſtle after having Deſcribed the Nature of Schiſm in the Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> Chap. 12. ſpends one whole Chapter more in praiſe of Charity; and ſetting forth its Adjuncts and Properties, doth touch upon thoſe things which ſeem in the Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick to be more eſpecially wanting.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 13, v. 4, 5, 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſuffereth long and is kind; Charity envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not; Charity vaunteth not it ſelf, is not puffed up, doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly, ſeeketh not her own, is not eaſily provoked, thinketh no Evil, rejoyceth not in Iniquity, but rejoyceth in the Truth; beareth all things, believeth all things, hopeth all things, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dureth all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Schiſmatick is not only Uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and thereby injurious to his Neighbour, but bringeth many and great Inconveniences upon himſelf, by cutting himſelf off from the Church of God, whence he is <hi>Condemned of himſelf,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Jude. v. 19.</note> and <hi>Separating themſelves they have not the Spirit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Jude.</hi> They have not the kind In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the Holy Spirit, whereby the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55533:30"/>Church is governed. Whence not only all their Gifts, but all their good works are utterly ſpoiled and come to nothing. As a Part cannot retain its Senſe and Life when it is cut off from the Body, as the Branch cannot bear Fruit except it <hi>abide in the Vine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John. 15.4.</note> as a Rivulet is ſoon dried up when ſeparated from the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; as a Ray cannot ſubſiſt when ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the Sun:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>St. Cyprian.</hi> de unitate Eccleſiae.</note> So neither can a Schiſmatick Reap any profit from his gifts or good works, when Separated from the reſt of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaketh as to both of them in the beginning of the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Chapter, concerning Gifts; <hi>Though I ſpeak with the Tongues of Men and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, though I have the gift of Propheſy and underſtand all Myſteries and all Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and though I have Faith ſo that I could remove Mountains, and have not Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, I am nothing.</hi> Again, concerning good Works; <hi>Though I beſtow all my Goods to feed the Poor, and though I give my Body to be Burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:55533:30"/>
            <p>Some are not ſenſible that it is any great harm to go amongſt them, to pray with them, or to hear the Goſpel Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But to joyn with them, in thoſe otherwiſe Holy Offices, is the way to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come partakers of their Sins.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 9.4.</note> 
               <hi>Their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices ſhall be unto them as the Bread of Mourning, all that eat thereof ſhall be Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted. Where two or three indeed are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together in</hi> Chriſt's <hi>Name,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> there is He <hi>in the midſt of them;</hi> but not when they are gathered againſt his Name, and againſt the other Members of the Church. Such Mens Prayers are not only Ineffectual, but Excrable. The Communion of Chriſt is but one. Among his Diſciples there is <hi>Peace.</hi> We muſt not Communicate with thoſe who break that Peace, leaſt we become <hi>partakers of their evil Deeds,</hi> and make the Breach wider by Encouraging of them. They are without the Church; and we muſt not be with them. For we cannot be within and without at the ſame time.<note place="margin">Mat. 12.30.</note> 
               <hi>He that is not with me is againſt me, and he that Gathereth
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55533:31"/>not with me Scattereth,</hi> ſaith our Saviour. Their Prayers and Preaching, and other parts of Divine Worſhip being performed in Oppoſition to the other Members of the Church, are turned into Sin; and they <hi>come together,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.17.</note> as did the <hi>Corinthians</hi> in a Diviſion of theirs, <hi>not for the better but for the worſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus we ſee how Schiſm is a work of the Fleſh againſt Chriſt's Kingdom, againſt the Goſpel, againſt the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion, againſt Virtue in general, againſt all the Apoſtolical Rules of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, very pernicious to the Church, very hurtful to the Schiſmatick himſelf, and of dangerous Conſequence to all that go after him.</p>
            <p>All things therefore are to be endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before we make a Schiſm, even Immoralities themſelves, where we are not made to concur with them, when it doth not belong to our Office to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form them, when it doth not lye in our Power to Reform them without break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in upon other Mens Rights, and doing Immoral Actions our ſelves. And then
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55533:31"/>certainly we are much more obliged to lay aſide private Advantages, <hi>not to ſeek our own,</hi> to let fall particular Quarrels for the ſake of the Church of Chriſt. And if our Governours ſhould deal hardly by us, and require difficult things of us in Divine Worſhip, not fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the main end of the Worſhip it ſelf; if ſome Words are improper, if ſome Ceremonies are uncouth, yet not hindring us from ſerving God <hi>with a pure Heart,</hi> we ought to bear with them. <hi>Charity beareth all things.</hi> It is a large Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, taking in all things that are tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Surely theſe indifferent things. And in a latter Schiſm here among us, Men ſeem to be hard put to it to find a Cauſe of Separation, when Proteſtants are forced to take up old Confuted Popery to ground it upon. If they had never ſo juſt a State-quarrel on the account of a Popiſh Prince, one would think they ſhould ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part with the Principles of their own Religion for the ſake of him. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude then with the Apoſtles Words,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Let us walk by the ſame Rule, let us mind
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55533:32"/>the ſame thing;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.19.</note> 
               <hi>Let us follow after the things which make for Peace, and thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> wherewith one may Edifie another;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>With all Lowlineſs and Meekneſs, with long Suffering, forbearing one another in Love; Endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>And let us Mark them which cauſe Diviſions and Offences contrary to the Doctrine which</hi> We <hi>have Learned, and avoid them.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
